# Nan Tang

Senior Scientist, Data Analytics Group Qatar Computing Research Institute (QCRI), HBKU Doha, Qatar

♠ +974 66700540 **☎** +974 44542850 ⊠ ntang@hbku.equ.qa da.qcri.org/ntang/ DOB: 28 September 1980

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

### Data Quality, Data Discovery, Internet of Things (IoT), Data Visualization

My main research interests are to build data quality and data discovery systems, which aim to solve the problem of finding, preparing, integrating, and cleaning datasets; these consider to consume at least 80% of data scientists's time in large enterprises.

### EDUCATION

2004/07–2007/12 Ph.D., Systems Engineering & Engineering Management

The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong

- Thesis: Efficient XPath Query Processing in Native XML Databases
- Co-Supervisors: Jeffrey Xu Yu and Kam-Fai Wong

2001/09-2004/01

M.Sc., Computer Science

Northeastern University, China

- Thesis: Parallel XML Databases
- Supervisor: Guoren Wang

1997/09-2001/01

B.S., Computer Science, Northeastern University, China

### Professional Experience

2015/04-now

Senior Scientist, Data Analytics, Qatar Computing Research Institute, Qatar.

2017/07-08

Visiting Scientist, CSAIL, MIT, US. Worked on the Data Civilizer project, with Michael Stonebraker, Samuel Madden, and Armando Solar-Lezama.

2011/12-2015/03

Scientist, Data Analytics, Qatar Computing Research Institute, Qatar.

2010/02-2012/01

Research fellow, University of Edinburgh, UK. Worked on data cleaning and graph algorithms, with Wenfei Fan.

2008/02-2010/01

 $Scientific\ staff\ member,\ \mathbf{CWI},\ \text{the\ Netherlands}.$  Worked on column-store database MonetDB and distributed XQuery processing, with Peter Boncz.

2007/03-08

Visiting Scholar, University of Waterloo, Canada. Worked on XML indexing and query rewriting, with Tamer Özsu.

### AWARDS

- 2015 Selected for best papers of PVLDB 2015, for my paper, titled "Lightning Fast and Space Efficient Inequality Joins".
- 2012 Selected for best papers of ICDE 2012, for my paper, titled "Incremental Detection of Inconsistencies in Distributed Data".
- The 37th VLDB conference, the Best Paper Award of VLDB 2010, for my paper, titled 2010 "Towards Certain Fixes with Editing Rules and Master Data".
- 2009 Selected for best papers of ICDE 2009, for my paper, titled "Projective Distribution of Full-Fledged XQuery".

### RESEARCH THEMES

### Data Quality

A commodity data cleaning system

- NADEEF: NADEEF (SIGMOD 2013, VLDB demo 2013, SIGMOD demo 2014) is the first commodity data cleaning system that allows the users to specify multiple types of data quality rules, as well as providing arbitrary data repairing algorithms, in a unified program interface.
  - BIGDANSING (SIGMOD 2015) powers NADEEF to run on top of most common general purpose data processing platforms, ranging from DBMSs to MapReduce-like frameworks.
  - Inequality join (PVLDB 2016, VLDBJ 2017) is inspired by a costly operation that joins tables on inequality conditions that are widely used in detecting data errors, e.g., by using denial constraints.

### Trusted Data Cleaning

Traditionally, integrity constraint based data repairing solutions target at computing a consistent database w.r.t. the given integrity constraints with the minimum cost. However, this "minimality" principle is nothing about the ground truth, hence these solutions are seldomly adopted in real applications. In contrast, a main area of my research is trusted data cleaning.

- Editing rules (VLDB 2010 best paper, VLDB Journal 2012) are the first work that repairs data while ensuring the correctness, by interacting with users and by using reference tables.
- o Fixing rules (SIGMOD 2014) are the first work to do automatic and trusted data repairing.
- FALCON (SIGMOD 2016) is a system that interacts with the user to decide SQL update queries, which actually encode fixing rules, to repair data.
- Sherlock rules (ICDE 2015) extend fixing rules by not only repairing data, but also annotating data as correct (proof positive) or wrong (proof negative), using reference tables.
- Detective rules (ICDE 2017) differ from Sherlock rules in that they draw evidence from trusted knowledge bases (in RDF format), not from reference tables (in tabular format).
- KATARA (SIGMOD 2015, VLDB demo 2015) is the first end-to-end data cleaning system powered by knowledge bases and crowdsourcing that interprets table semantics, identifies correct and wrong data, and generates top-k possible repairs.

## Resolution

- Entity SynthesizER (SIGMOD demo 2017, PVLDB 2017) studies the problem of synthesizing concise and interpretable entity matching rules from examples, using program synthesis.
- and Deeper (under submission to ICDE 2018) leverages the idea of distributed representations Consolidation and representation learning from deep learning to significantly improve the accuracy of entity resolution over the state-of-the-art solutions.
  - Data Currency (ICDE 2013) identifies the most current values for duplicate records.

#### Data Discovery

# Civilizer

Data With thousands of disparate data sources, data discovery is more important than ever to help analysts consolidate valuable sources and solve analytical tasks.

• DATA CIVILIZER (CIDR 2017, SIGMOD demo 2017) is a generalized pipeline that finds, integrates, and cleans datasets to facilitate large companies to do analytical tasks.

### Internet of Things

Stream Management

Graph • TCM (SIGMOD 2016) is a graphical sketch for graph streams. Traditional sketches have 1dimensional structures (or simply counters). TCM is 2-dimensional that keeps all connections of the graph stream, which supports a much more graph queries than existing sketches.

### Data Visualization

### Data

Visualization

- Automatic Deepeye (under submission to ICDE 2018) is an automatic data visualization system:
  - 1. Visualization recognition: given a visualization, e.g., a bar chart or a pie chart for a given dataset, is it "good" or "bad", from an understanding of human perception?
  - 2. Visualization ranking: given two visualizations for the same dataset, which one is "better"?
  - 3. Visualization selection: given a dataset, how to compute top-k visualizations?

### TEACHING AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE

### Internship Mentor, QCRI

Jinsong Guo	Ph.D. from University of Oxford, UK, on Calibrating data errors	2017/03 - 2017/09
Dong Deng	Ph.D. from Tsinghua University, China, on Data Civilizer	2016/06 - 2016/08
Sourav Medya	Ph.D. from UCSB, US, on Mining data streams	2016/06 - 2016/08
Qing Chen	Master from Fudan University, China, on Graph stream summarization	2015/07 - 2016/04
Jian He	Master from Tsinghua University, China, on Falcon	2014/11 - 2015/02
Matteo Interlandi	Ph.D. from University of Modena, Italy, on Sherlock rules	2014/03 - 2014/05
Chu Xu	Ph.D. from University of Waterloo, Canada, on Katara	2013/05 - 2014/07
Jiannan Wang	Ph.D. from Tsinghua University, China, on Fixing rules	2012/12 - 2013/02
Yu Tang	Master from Hong Kong University, HK, on Nadeef dashboard	2012/11 - 2013/01
Amr Ebaid	Ph.D. from Purdue University, US, on NADEEF	2012/04-2013/01
Ahmed Eldawy	Ph.D. from University of Minnesota, US, on Nadeef	2012/01  2012/05
Michele Dallachiesa	Ph.D. from University of Trento, Italy, on NADEEF	2012/01-2012/05

### Teaching, University of Edinburgh, UK (Tutorials)

Applied Databases 2010/09-11

### Teaching, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong (Tutorials)

Digital Logical and Systems	2006/09-12, 2007/09-12
Fundamentals of Information Systems	2004/09-12, 2006/01-05
Information Systems Design & Analysis	2005/01-05

### Selected Professional Activities and Services

Iournal	Reviewer
Journal	neviewer

VLDB Journal	2009, 2010, 2011
IEEE Trans. on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE)	2007,2011,2012,2016
ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (TKDD)	2012
ACM Transactions on Database Systems (TODS)	2013
ACM Transactions on the Web (TWEB)	2012, 2015

### PC Member

ACM Transactions on the Web (TWEB)

ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (SIGMOD) 2015, 2017, 2018
International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (PVLDB)

IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE)

International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT)

SIAM International Conference on Data Mining (SDM)

ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM)

2012, 2015

2017, 2018

2018

2019

2019

2017

2017

### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

### Journal Publications

- 1. Rohit Singh, Vamsi Meduri, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Samuel Madden, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Armando Solar-Lezama, and Nan Tang. Synthesizing Entity Matching Rules by Examples. PVLDB, 2017.
- 2. Zuhair Khayyat, William Lucia, Meghna Singh, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Panos Kalnis. Fast and Scalable Inequality Joins. VLDB Journal, 2017 (Special issue: Best Papers of VLDB 2015, invited).
- 3. Shuang Hao, Nan Tang, Guoliang Li, Jian He, Na Ta, and Jianhua Feng. A Novel Cost-Based Model for Data Repairing. IEEE Transaction on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE), 2017.
- 4. Jiannan Wang, and Nan Tang. Dependable Data Repairing with Fixing Rules. ACM Journal of Data and Information Quality (JDIQ), 2017.

- 5. Ziawasch Abedjan, Xu Chu, Dong Deng, Raul Castro Fernandez, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Michael Stonebraker, and Nan Tang. *Data Cleaning: Where are we and what needs to be done?* [Experiments and Analyses]. PVLDB, 2016.
- Zuhair Khayyat, William Lucia, Meghna Singh, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, Panos Kalnis. Lightning Fast and Space Efficient Inequality Joins. PVLDB, 2015.
- 7. Wenfei Fan, Floris Geerts, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Conflict Resolution with Data Currency and Consistency. ACM Journal of Data and Information Quality (JDIQ), 2014 (invited).
- 8. Wenfei Fan, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Interaction between Record Matching and Data Repairing. ACM Journal of Data and Information Quality (JDIQ), 2014.
- 9. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Incremental Detection of Inconsistencies in Distributed Data. IEEE Transaction on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE), 2014 (Special issue: Best Papers of ICDE 2012, invited).
- 10. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Yinghui Wu. Adding Regular Expressions to Graph Reachability and Pattern Queries. Frontiers of Computer Science, 2012 (Special issues: New Topics in Database, invited).
- 11. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Towards Certain Fixes with Editing Rules and Master Data. VLDB Journal, 2012 (Special issue: Best Papers of VLDB 2010, invited).
- 12. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Towards Certain Fixes with Editing Rules and Master Data. In PVLDB, 2010 (The Best Paper award).
- 13. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Yinghui Wu, Yunpeng Wu. *Graph Pattern Matching: From Intractable to Polynomial Time*. In PVLDB, 2010.
- 14. Ying Zhang, Nan Tang, Peter Boncz. *Projective Distribution of Full-Fledged XQuery*. IEEE Transaction on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE), 2010 (Special issue: *Best Papers of ICDE 2009*, *invited*).
- 15. Kam-Fai Wong, Jeffrey Xu Yu, and Nan Tang. Answering XML queries using path-based indexes: A survey. World Wide Web Journal, 2006.

### Conference Publications

- Saravanan Thirumuruganathan, Laure Berti-Equille, Mourad Ouzzani, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz and Nan Tang. UGuide – User-Guided Discovery of FD-Detectable Errors. SIGMOD, 2017.
- Raul Castro Fernandez, Dong Deng, Essam Mansour, Abdulhakim Qahtan, Wenbo Tao, Ziawasch Abedjan, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Samuel Madden, Mourad Ouzzani, Michael Stonebraker and Nan Tang. A Demo of the Data Civilizer System. SIGMOD demo, 2017.
- 3. Rohit Singh, Vamsi Meduri, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Samuel Madden, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Armando Solar-Lezama and Nan Tang. *Generating Concise Entity Matching Rules*. SIGMOD demo, 2017.
- 4. Shuang Hao, Nan Tang, Guoliang Li and Jian Li. Cleaning Relations using Knowledge Bases. ICDE, 2017.
- Dong Deng, Raul Castro Fernandez, Ziawasch Abedjan, Sibo Wang, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Samuel Madden, Mourad Ouzzani and Nan Tang. The Data Civilizer System. CIDR, 2017.
- 6. Nan Tang, Qing Chen, and Prasenjit Mitra. Graph Stream Summarization. SIGMOD, 2016.
- 7. Jian He, Enzo Veltri, Donatello Santoro, Guoliang Li, Giansalvatore Mecca, Paolo Papotti, and Nan Tang. *Interactive and Deterministic Data Cleaning*. SIGMOD, 2016.
- 8. Divy Agrawal, M. Lamine Ba, Laure Berti-Equille, Sanjay Chawla, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Hossam Hammady, Yasser Idris, Zoi Kaoudi, Zuhair Khayyat, Sebastian Kruse, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Mohammed J. Zaki. *Rheem: Enabling Multi-Platform Task Execution*. SIGMOD demo, 2016.

- 9. Divy Agrawal, Sanjay Chawla, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Zoi Kaoudi, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Mohammed J. Zaki. *RHEEM: Road to Freedom in Big Data Analytics*. EDBT (vision paper), 2016.
- Xu Chu, John Morcos, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Nan Tang, and Yin Ye. KATARA: A Data Cleaning System Powered by Knowledge Bases and Crowdsourcing. SIGMOD, 2015.
- 11. Xu Chu, John Morcos, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Nan Tang, and Yin Ye. KATARA: Reliable Data Cleaning with Knowledge Bases and Crowdsourcing. VLDB demo, 2015.
- 12. Zuhair Khayyat, Ihab F. Ilyas, Alekh Jindal, Sam Madden, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge-Arnulfo Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Si Yin. *BigDansing: A System for Big Data Cleansing*. SIGMOD, 2015.
- 13. Nan Tang. Big RDF Data Cleaning. The 6th International Workshop on Data Engineering meets the Semantic Web (DESWeb), in conjunction with ICDE, 2015 (invited).
- 14. Matteo Interlandi and Nan Tang. Proof Positive and Negative in Data Cleaning. ICDE, 2015.
- 15. Nan Tang. Big Data Cleaning. APWeb, 2014 (invited as Distinguished Lecture Series).
- 16. Jiannan Wang and Nan Tang. Towards Dependable Data Repairing with Fixing Rules. SIGMOD, 2014.
- 17. Ahmed Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, Jorge Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Si Yin. *NADEEF/ER: Generic and Interactive Entity Resolution*. SIGMOD demo, 2014.
- 18. Michele Dallachiesa, Amr Ebaid, Ahmed Eldawy, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, and Nan Tang. *NADEEF: A Commodity Data Cleaning System*. SIGMOD, 2013.
- 19. Amr Ebaid, Ahmed Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Mourad Ouzzani, Jorge Quiane-Ruiz, Nan Tang, and Si Yin. *NADEEF: A Generalized Data Cleaning System*. VLDB demo, 2013.
- 20. Wenfei Fan, Floris Geerts, Nan Tang, and Wenyuan Yu. Inferring Data Currency and Consistency for Conflict Resolution. ICDE, 2013.
- 21. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Nan Tang, and Wenyuan Yu. Incremental Detection of Inconsistencies in Distributed Data. ICDE, 2012.
- 22. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. CerFix: A System for Cleaning Data with Certain Fixes. VLDB demo, 2011.
- 23. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Wenyuan Yu. Interaction between record matching and data repairing. SIGMOD, 2011.
- 24. Wenfei Fan, Jianzhong Li, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, Yinghui Wu. Adding Regular Expressions to Graph Reachability and Pattern Queries. ICDE, 2011.
- 25. Nan Tang, Lefteris Sidirourgos, Peter Boncz. Space-Economical Q-Gram Index for Exact String Matching. CIKM, 2009.
- Ying Zhang, Nan Tang, Peter Boncz. Efficient Distribution of Full-Fledged XQuery. ICDE, 2009.
- 27. Nan Tang, Jeffrey Xu Yu, Hao Tang, M. Tamer Özsu and Peter Boncz. *Materialized View Selection in XML Databases*. DASFAA, 2009.
- 28. Nan Tang, Jeffrey Xu Yu, M. Tamer Özsu, Byron Choi, and Kam-Fai Wong. Multiple materialized view selection for XPath query rewriting. ICDE, 2008.
- Nan Tang, Jeffrey Xu Yu, M. Tamer Özsu, and Kam-Fai Wong. Hierarchical indexing approaches to support XPath queries. ICDE, 2008.
- 30. Nan Tang, Guoren Wang, Jeffrey Xu Yu, Kam-Fai Wong, and Ge Yu. Win: An effcient data placement strategy for parallel XML databases. In Proc. 11th International Conference on Parallel and Distributed System (ICPADS), 2005.

### Miscellaneous Writings

1. Mourad Ouzzani and Nan Tang, contributors to the chapter "The Data Civilizer System", for *Michael Stonebraker ACM A.M. Turing Award Book*, under preparation (*invited*).

- 2. Wenfei Fan, Floris Geerts, Shuai Ma, Nan Tang, and Wenyuan Yu. *Data Quality Problems beyond Consistency and Deduplication*. In search of elegance in the theory and practice of computation: a Festschrift in honour of Peter Buneman, Edinburgh, UK, 2013 (*invited*).
- 3. George Beskales, Gautam Das, Ahmed K. Elmagarmid, Ihab F. Ilyas, Felix Naumann, Mourad Ouzzani, Paolo Papotti, Jorge Quiane-Ruiz, and Nan Tang. *The Data Analytics Group at the Qatar Computing Research Institute*. SIGMOD Record, 2012.

### Patents

- 1. Dependable Data Repairing with Fixing Rules. Qatar Computing Research Institute, HBKU (PCT/EP2013/052476).
- 2. Towards dependable Data Repairing with Fixing Rules. Qatar Computing Research Institute, HBKU (PCT/EP2014/052494).
- 3. Katara: A Data Cleaning System Powered by Knowledge Bases and Crowdsourcing. Qatar Computing Research Institute, HBKU (PCT/GB2014/051670).
- 4. Nadeef: A holistic and extensible data cleaning platform. Qatar Computing Research Institute, HBKU (PCT/EP2012/062446).
- 5. Generalized Data Cleaning using SAT-Solvers. Qatar Computing Research Institute, HBKU (PCT/EP2012/062445).

### INVITED TALKS

- 2016/10 "Data Cleaning Techniques", at Harvard University, US
- 2016/03 "Graph Stream Summarization", at MIT, US
- 2015/12 "Trusted Data Cleaning", at KAUST, Saudi Arabia
- 2015/04 "Big RDF Data Cleaning", at the 6th International Workshop on Data Engineering meets the Semantic Web (DESWeb), in conjunction with ICDE 2015
- 2014/09 "Big Data Cleaning" at Asia-Pacific Web Conference 2014, Distinguished Lecturer series

### References

Michael Stonebraker Adjunct Professor, MIT stonebraker@csail.mit.edu

Ihab Ilyas Professor, University of Waterloo ilyas@uwaterloo.ca

Jeffrey Xu Yu Professor, Chinese University of HK yu@se.cuhk.edu.hk Samuel Madden
Professor, MIT
madden@csail.mit.edu

Ahmed Elmagarmid Executive Director of QCRI aelmagarmid@hbku.edu.qa